<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev</id>
  <title>Halloumi Thoughts</title>
  <updated>2026-01-08T20:24:02.882685+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>halloumithoughts</name>
    <email>hidden</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/feed/" rel="self"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <subtitle>My rumblings on life, art, cinema, literature, and culture</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/31122025/</id>
    <title>31/12/2025</title>
    <updated>2025-12-31T13:39:27.104437+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Somebody added my film blog (&lt;a href='https://halloumiseason.evdokimovas.com'&gt;Halloumi Season&lt;/a&gt;) to their blog roll! It makes me so happy :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/31122025/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-31T13:39:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/221225/</id>
    <title>22/12/25</title>
    <updated>2025-12-22T20:55:37.240544+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seams like I've just finished writing my thesis, binged through 11 episodes of &lt;em&gt;House M.D.&lt;/em&gt; in one sitting, and redesigned my portfolio (and I even think I like the new design)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/221225/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-22T20:55:37.240301+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/keep-your-ai-productivity-in-your-pants/</id>
    <title>Keep your AI productivity in your pants</title>
    <updated>2025-12-21T18:47:30.004111+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, yet again doing anything but writing my thesis, I, for the Nth time, started thinking about my &lt;a href='https://halloumiseason.evdokimovas.com'&gt;film blog&lt;/a&gt; and how I want to write enormously more reviews and other interesting stuff and grow a newsletter. I started thinking (again) about available newsletter platforms. I redid my "research", decided I will go with Ghost for that, and yada, yada, yada. At one point I went to Ghost's explore page; not only because I wanted to see some of the themes in action, but also because I like blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely, there's an aura around Ghost.io created by those all entrepreneur-creator-make-a-pile-of-money-out-of-nowhere-in-a-day productivity gurus, albeit I way underestimated how many times I'd see either become-rich-meditating type of content or how many AI generated images (or for that matter texts, but I couldn't bring myself to read them to confirm they were AI generated) in bananas I'd scroll through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's just sad. The individualistic moods covered under the fake veil of get-rich-quickly promises just make me sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long ago, I came to a decision of not reading, supporting or somehow engaging with anything that has to do with AI – if the author didn't have any respect for me as a reader to write a post, edit it, share their thoughts, think about, then I, as a reader, don't want to show them respect that comes with me reading it. I don't understand why we all collectively started treating "fine enough" as "good" and "to strive for". Why would anyone who can do good do just enough to pass? And more importantly, I don't understand, why I would consume something that is not good and has value (at least of being thoughtfully created), but something that is passible enough and has different number of fingers in every scene and 8257038475236 em dashes and phrases that Chomsky would write instead of "Colorless green ideas sleep furiously"?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/keep-your-ai-productivity-in-your-pants/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="english"/>
    <published>2025-12-21T18:47:30.003744+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/20122025/</id>
    <title>20/12/2025</title>
    <updated>2025-12-20T10:37:13.312314+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past three days I've been trying to write my entire thesis in one day. The thing is that that I have an unlimited and almost unregulated access to &lt;em&gt;House M.D.&lt;/em&gt;. (I'm at 1/3 of my writing, tho)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/20122025/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-20T10:37:13.311892+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/design-moving-homes-and-winery-photos/</id>
    <title>Design, moving homes, and winery photos</title>
    <updated>2025-12-13T21:58:02.362463+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was having a usual design-is-easy (if you're not a designer) / AI-is-the-best-tool-for-designers conversation, and something clicked inside – I was thinking to myself about how I don't want to engage in any design-related conversations with non designers. And, maybe, actually, this 'revelation' and decision propagated in me a couple of weeks ago when I came to a conclusion that "well, no, you can not call yourself a designer if you watched 3 YouTube videos"; how many are there people who use Canva templates, printing them into small stores logos and non-like-others (actually the most popular in the area) coffeeshops' menus, taking money for that 2-minute lazy jobs?. I may sound very judgmental in both regards, albeit I'd rather be cutting off the conversation in the very beginning than engaging with people who state their opinions so shamelessly confidently whilst not knowing a thing they tend to rumble about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the brighter side of this week, after living where I live for the past 10 years, it's been the first time when I got to another community other than my town about which I've had a though that "well, I really can see myself moving here" – and the place is completely the opposite of what I love my town for. I find this very intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/winery-4.webp" alt="winery 4" /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/winery-3.webp" alt="winery 3" /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/project_20120101_0005.webp" alt="Project_20120101_0005" /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/winery-2.webp" alt="winery 2" /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/winery-1.webp" alt="winery 1" /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/project_20120101_0003.webp" alt="Project_20120101_0003" /&gt;
&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/halloumithoughts/project_20120101_0004.webp" alt="Project_20120101_0004" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/design-moving-homes-and-winery-photos/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="english"/>
    <published>2025-12-13T21:39:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/131225/</id>
    <title>13/12/25</title>
    <updated>2025-12-13T00:26:43.218347+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve just watched &lt;em&gt;The silence of the lambs&lt;/em&gt;, and oh boy how a lot of angry rumblings I gotta write for my film blog&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/131225/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-13T00:26:43.218137+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/came-on-christmas/</id>
    <title>Came on, Christmas</title>
    <updated>2025-12-10T18:46:06.123546+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I may be getting older and much more cantankerous – it's been the second year in a row when I don't get the Christmas-New Year season. It's almost annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the New Year used to be my favourite holiday – getting all together with my family, having the celebration exclusive dishes cooked by my mother and my ants, writing letters to Santa Claus with my cousins, and getting reasonable gifts – it all used to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now thought it all feels fabricated, fake, and plastic. That feels dystopian. The stores are flooded by cheaply made useless junk and people, who are going to buy it all only to throw it out the next year to make room for the stuff that fits into their ever-changing trend-induce aesthetic next year better. I don't remember the last time I got myself new Christmas ornaments nor do I remember trying to fit Christmas to whichever newly made 'aesthetic'. I don't remember getting loads and loads of presents nor getting something shamelessly expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe, it's not what the majority of people are having and it’s only what social media makes it to appear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It got to the point when I don't want to decorate my house and take out the christmas tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope to rebuild the childlike spirit I used to have all those years somewhere in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/came-on-christmas/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="english"/>
    <published>2025-12-10T18:45:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/08122025/</id>
    <title>08/12/2025</title>
    <updated>2025-12-08T18:09:04.390350+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The only thing I’ve been doing lately is illustrating and designing magazine spreads – I’m more than content to spend my time in such a manner&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/08122025/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-08T18:09:04.390142+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/061225/</id>
    <title>06/12/25</title>
    <updated>2025-12-06T00:22:26.428318+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My biggest fail as of now is that I didn’t answer Angelo Badalamenti’s cameo in Mulholland Dr. in a quiz game. I guess, Mulholland Dr. rewatching and an analysis are coming&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/061225/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-06T00:22:26.427999+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/021225/</id>
    <title>02/12/25</title>
    <updated>2025-12-02T21:18:08.328521+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>halloumithoughts</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I definitely should start writing more. All I do is think about writing and gathering ideas for the essays that will not likely see the light of day. I think, I can promise myself to write and draw as soon as I'm done with all the projects I need to get ready before the deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://halloumithoughts.bearblog.dev/021225/" rel="alternate"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <published>2025-12-02T21:08:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>