<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>bearblog</id>
  <title>Bear Blog Trending Posts</title>
  <updated>2026-01-09T06:11:23.341381+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Bear Blog</name>
    <email>feed@bearblog.dev</email>
  </author>
  <link href="https://bearblog.dev/discover/" rel="alternate"/>
  <generator uri="https://lkiesow.github.io/python-feedgen" version="0.9.0">python-feedgen</generator>
  <subtitle>Trending posts on Bear Blog</subtitle>
  <entry>
    <id>https://robertbirming.com/still-there-happy/</id>
    <title>Still there, still happy</title>
    <updated>2026-01-08T05:09:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>robert</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/robert/img_0797_original.webp" alt="Seamstress" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Seamstress in Chiang Mai, Thailand.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first saw this lovely lady when I visited Chiang Mai back in 2014. Yesterday, I saw her again and asked if I could take a photo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was still sitting in the very same spot. A small street-side shelter made of bamboo and tarps, where she runs her sewing business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how old she is, but I wouldn’t be surprised if she’s close to 70. It felt as if she hadn’t aged a day during the decade that had passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was just sitting there, looking genuinely content and peaceful, sewing away. As if nothing needed to change or happen for her to be truly happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe that’s the secret to true happiness, being thankful for what we have, here and now. We may have plans and ambitions, but we don’t let them overshadow the value of the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is all we have.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://robertbirming.com/still-there-happy/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-08T05:09:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://leavethefeed.bearblog.dev/the-lack-of-trust-on-the-internet-is-exhausting/</id>
    <title>The lack of trust on the internet is exhausting.</title>
    <updated>2026-01-07T18:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>leavethefeed</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This morning I read &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/fault-lines/what-a-viral-youtube-video-says-about-the-future-of-journalism"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; piece in the New Yorker about the 23 year old Youtuber Nick Shirley who went viral a few days ago after posting a video in which he visited a variety of daycare centres alleged to have committed fraud. The tone of the NY piece is understandably defeatist, if you go to the video there are thousands of comments praising it, commenting on how it's the future of journalism and how we should be applauding this young man for breaking this major story. Of course, the story had been broken and many of the claims are &lt;a href="https://www.snopes.com/news/2025/12/30/nick-shirley-minnesota-daycare-fraud/"&gt;outright false&lt;/a&gt;, there are barely any sources, there are ai generated images spliced in and the whole thing is fairly obvious ragebait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, when searching for answers on this topic, which admittedly is a complex one, you can't trust anything on Reddit or god forbid any other social media, there are obvious bad actors everywhere (on both sides!). What stuck out for me is the sense of confusion and lack of trust I had on any source in regards to this story wasn't a new one, it's something I've had been feeling for years now, and a feeling not just relegated to news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another strange example, I'm into my photography. I take a lot of pictures and I always have, I also love the hardware part of the hobby. I understand that gear only gets you so far, but I'm interested in both old and new digital cameras in the way old men who stand with their hands behind their backs peering into construction sites are - I just want to know what's going on. There are a few Youtube channels I'll go on to use as a sort of newsfeed for camera stuff, comfort watching or I'll occasionally search a model number of one of my cameras to see if I can find anything new about it. What I've noticed is that camera youtubers, like all youtubers, are trapped by the algorithm. This was made blazingly obvious to me when I noticed that so many of them have a video that looks a lot like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/leavethefeed/photos.webp" alt="a bunch of clickbait nonsense" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, each of these videos is nonsense, the 'film' look these guys talk about is always super vague, in a way that fits with the images that whatever camera these guys are talking about produces. To get the 'film' look with a digital camera, turn up the iso, spam the flash and learn the basics of color grading and the tone curve. These things take time to learn, and well, don't make for very fun videos to watch. The problem with clickbait-y videos like this on these channels is that they erode trust, how am I supposed to take anything these people say seriously now when I know they've just hopped on a silly little trend for the sole purpose of attracting eyeballs to make number go up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gets me to my main point. Here on bear, and on the indieweb in general, we don't really have this problem. People post mostly for themselves, and yes there are people trying to gain large followings, but they aren't playing to an algorithm that values attention and engagement over everything, they're trying to get there by offering something unique to their readers. When I browse the discover and the new sections my mind doesn't go to that doubting, cynical state straight away. Instead, I read posts. Either I have no idea about what I'm reading, in which case I get to learn something new, or someone is posting about something they're incredibly passionate about, in which case, great I love that too! In both cases I know that the post was written for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; first - I'm just a bystander, watching with my hands behind my back, before moving on to the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://leavethefeed.bearblog.dev/the-lack-of-trust-on-the-internet-is-exhausting/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-07T18:06:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nickhayes.bearblog.dev/my-newold-ipodnano/</id>
    <title>I just wanted to show off my new old iPod</title>
    <updated>2026-01-07T13:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>nickhayes</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My new old iPod Nano arrived today in the exact colour I always wanted as a kid, and now it's mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/nickhayes/img_4935.webp" alt="IMG_4935" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish someone had a camera angled at me to capture the massive smile on my face as I plugged in my wired earphones and pressed play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd say this is £35 well spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can listen to all of my k-pop albums without an internet connection, just like god intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; {{ previous_post }} • {{ next_post }} &lt;/center&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://nickhayes.bearblog.dev/my-newold-ipodnano/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-07T13:31:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://xtoblog.bearblog.dev/you-guys-are-boring/</id>
    <title>you guys are boring</title>
    <updated>2026-01-07T00:42:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>xtoblog</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Listen; I’m boring too. But can a couple of nerds on some seemingly obscure internet platform with mild social media settings come up with something more fun to talk about than AI and leftist viewpoints ? It’s so nice to see niche blogs, I read them even if I can’t figure out what they’re talking about. There is something so pure in somebody else’s passion. But I can also tell when everyone is just posting stuff to say something for the algorithm. If I wanted news analysis I would watch the news, if I wanted Ai analysis I would watch a YouTube video about AI and the doom and gloom about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So get up and make something fun, for your own sake ! And for everyone else stuck reading blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://xtoblog.bearblog.dev/you-guys-are-boring/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-07T00:42:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://robertbirming.com/not-judging/</id>
    <title>I’m not judging, but…</title>
    <updated>2026-01-06T13:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>robert</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I overheard a discussion during breakfast. Actually, a &lt;em&gt;monologue&lt;/em&gt; would be a better way to describe it. It just went on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started with “I’m not judging anyone, but...”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he went on non-stop about how terrible people were. His boss was a psychopath, the ex-wife was a narcissist, his friend was a liar, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it feels like being unhappy makes people happy, in a false kind of way. Like they derive their sense of identity from being “the unlucky one”. As if “bad things always happen to me” is their personality, or at least a big part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They manage to find faults in every person and problems in every situation. They have to, to stay alive. No problem, no persona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, maybe this person really was one unlucky dude. Who am I to judge.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://robertbirming.com/not-judging/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-06T13:47:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://arrozdoce.bearblog.dev/the-more-i-read-blogs-the-more-we-are-the-same/</id>
    <title>The more I read blogs, the more we are the same</title>
    <updated>2026-01-06T08:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>arrozdoce</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The more I read blogs, the more I feel my thoughts are similar to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I click on the links in the discovery page and on other webrings, people write about their lack of focus, hardships and feeling alone. Society has always been the same but now it is in our face 24/7 due to social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to write another doom and gloom post because there are plenty out there. We need to focus on the positive and remember there are people out there going through worse than ourselves. The world has much good to offer but it rarely makes the news if you know what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing blog posts and journalling help us get through the thoughts and feelings. We are all on this small planet doing our best at the end of the day. This is our journey of life, good or bad, these are the chapters of our book. Remember, chapters end and new ones begin. Any day can be a fresh start and don't wait for New Years to experience it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://arrozdoce.bearblog.dev/the-more-i-read-blogs-the-more-we-are-the-same/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-06T08:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://brnt.sh/fuck-your-atomic-habits/</id>
    <title>fuck your atomic habits</title>
    <updated>2026-01-06T03:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>brent</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fuck your atomic habits&lt;br /&gt;
Your dopaminergic nootropics&lt;br /&gt;
Your four hour workweek&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fuck your bujo&lt;br /&gt;
Your calibrated microdose&lt;br /&gt;
Your Wim Hof human potential&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And fuck your GTD&lt;br /&gt;
Your perfectly chubby FIRE&lt;br /&gt;
Your lifechanging magic of tidying up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fuck your crucial conversations&lt;br /&gt;
Your calculated lean in&lt;br /&gt;
Your impressively deep fucking work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come as you were&lt;br /&gt;
Bothered, unmoisturized&lt;br /&gt;
Taking up all the lanes&lt;br /&gt;
Inbox infinity, unstyled&lt;br /&gt;
Fried, half asleep&lt;br /&gt;
No transformative frameworks&lt;br /&gt;
No plan&lt;br /&gt;
Nowhere special&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey, you’re here now&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://brnt.sh/fuck-your-atomic-habits/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-06T03:36:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.absurdpirate.com/sitting-on-the-fence-like-that/</id>
    <title>careful you don't split your ass sitting on the fence like that</title>
    <updated>2026-01-08T21:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>absurdpirate</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've been paying attention to the news you probably are aware of the murder of Renee Good at the hands of ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And unfortunately, this is where the useless apathetic takes come out. The useless commentary of people who want nothing more than to self-aggrandize on how little of an opinion they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It must be nice being so damn obtuse to the situation at hand that you can sit in a nice place of privilege and arrogantly try and claim both sides as just as bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both sides aren't killing people, both sides aren't violently harassing citizens, both sides aren't justifying lethal use of force from the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all you're gonna do is stick that fence post firmly up your ass and &amp;quot;both sides&amp;quot; the situation to death, then your best course of action is to shut the fuck up, because your &amp;quot;commentary&amp;quot; is about as useful as a broken refrigerator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have nothing intelligent to offer besides surface-level observations, your opinion has already been done to death by mainstream news outlets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your apathy is at best cowardice, and at worst evil. If you're the type of person to think how Renee was &amp;quot;insignificant&amp;quot; and thus you don't care. Let this be a reminder that you are a piece of shit. How many people need to die before you realize you're just a sociopath masquerading as an intellectual?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're not enlightened for being a &amp;quot;centrist&amp;quot;. If you're ignorant of the situation, that's fine, but don't go trying to act like both sides are equally bad in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you watched a woman getting murdered in her car trying to escape a bunch of fascist-backed thugs and think &amp;quot;bOtH sIdEs&amp;quot; you need to find a proctologist to have your head surgically removed from your own ass.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://blog.absurdpirate.com/sitting-on-the-fence-like-that/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-08T21:01:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://haru-txt.bearblog.dev/laptop-longevity/</id>
    <title>Your Laptop Has More Than Three Years in It</title>
    <updated>2026-01-07T20:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>haru-txt</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm writing this post from a very noisy Asus gaming laptop. One of the fan broke again. It was last serviced in August for this exact same reason. Apparently a piece of plastic from the broken right hinge got into the fan and destroyed it. Thankfully I couldn't hear the noise with my headphones on, and I'm writing this in a dead mall where my laptop repair shop is located. I have been their customer since 2021 when I dropped this laptop from the top bunk of a bed (don't ask). No wonder the hinge is messed up now. Since then the laptop has issues here and there, but for the most part it works all right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I got this laptop in 2020,&amp;quot; I told the repairman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh? That's great. These days, getting more than three years out of a gaming laptop is good.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the fuck,&lt;/em&gt; I thought. Then I thought of how my more affluent friends trade in their electronics for the newer version &lt;em&gt;every year&lt;/em&gt;. I guess that's the reality nowadays. When did that become the new normal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of my tech are secondhand. Before this laptop, I used a 2011 iMac my dad got from his friend from 2013 to 2018, then an old MacBook Pro (I don't remember the year but it was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; old, about the same age as the iMac) from 2018 to 2020. Both of these macs died for reasons unknown and I thought I already got my money's worth out of them, so as a replacement I got this Laptop new around mid-2020 according to the oldest file I can find on it. I've been using it pretty much every day since, mostly for writing and indie gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the phone front, I've been using an iPhone 7 Plus since roughly 2019. Its battery has degraded and I never replace it. &amp;quot;I'm replacing this phone soon anyway,&amp;quot; I told people. I've been telling people that since then and still to this day (the phone is charging next to me as we speak). It still works. Barely, but as long as the banking apps work I consider that &amp;quot;working&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm used to using gadgets until they literally died in my arms. And I'm not gentle with them either. My phone has been thrown against the wall out of rage (not caused by it) more than once. My iPad is naked because I chose to spend my money on buffet and ice cream over a new case. They're still holding up aside from the short charging port scare. I thought this was the default way of using tech until I met my rich friends. Then I thought that's just what rich people do until I realise the rest of us are also trading in our perfectly usable phones and laptops for newer ones given the chance. Now I look insane going to repair shop in a dead mall trying to squeeze more out of my aging laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Society at large have gotten used to the idea that tech is either brand-spanking new or completely unusable, and anything between those is not just unacceptable but a completely unknown concept. The problem with that is it's only possible for something to be new for so long, so the moment a gadget gets older than… I don't even know what's the acceptable age for a tech item anymore, it's regarded as &amp;quot;too old&amp;quot; and traded in for a new, shiny one. It's so easy to do so these days — you can go to an &lt;a href="https://haru-txt.bearblog.dev/evil-apple-store/"&gt;evil and intimidating&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup class="footnote-ref" id="fnref-1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Apple Store and get your data transferred to a new phone in seconds. It's way harder to actually fix your phone. I don't know how to do it myself either but I assume that if my local sketchy repair shop can replace Nan's iPhone 6 camera with a new (albeit worse) camera then it can be done. Or maybe you can't do it with a newer iPhones. I don't know anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is, maybe we shouldn't do this? Maybe we should learn to live with slightly (or not so slightly) scuffed tech that still works? I genuinely don't know who started the idea of trading in. Apple? Microsoft? Capitalism as a whole?! Here are a couple reasons why we shouldn't do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It's overconsumption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are making unnecessary purchases by trading in your perfectly usable tech for a new one. Even if you don't care about wasting money (which you should, but you do you. I also waste my money on overpriced ice cream), you probably should care about the environment since I assume you people reading this are going to be sticking around for at least another half a century. Now I don't know where traded-in electronics go. I assume they get refurbished and resold (if they don't end up in the landfill). That's still extra packaging that need to be manufactured and shipped. I'm not a particularly eco sort, but I still think we should reduce the amount of consumption overall. Buy less, not buy eco, you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The upgrades are actually worse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enshittification is real, you guys. I don't even think this is an intentional, malicious doing to purposefully break your device so you buy a new one. I think people in Big Tech are genuinely either incompetent or replaced by AI. I run Windows 11. Every update breaks something. It's horrible. On the hardware side of thing, things break faster. Colors oxidises and chips. Hinges break at the slightest of hand. And the worst part is if your stuff doesn't break...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technology has mostly plateaued&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you're somehow stuck with a phone from 2016 like I am, a new phone in 2026 isn't going to load up your content any faster than your current one does. Any faster and that's breaking the laws of physics. If you aren't able to stream a 4K video from YouTube without buffering, it's probably your internet's fault. We have long reached the point of diminishing return when it comes to technology. New phones aren't defined by their upgraded hardware specs but their (probably vibecoded) software-side features. Cameras have only been improving on the computational side for the past few years. MacBooks haven't had any significant innovation in them for years and everyone knows it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion: just use what you already have until it dies. Don't just get a new one at the smallest of your inconvenience. Whatever problem you're having right now isn't going to be fixed with a new phone. You don't need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;See how I'm being clever by being self-referential? Now subscribe.&lt;a href="#fnref-1" class="footnote"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://haru-txt.bearblog.dev/laptop-longevity/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-07T20:26:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://haru-txt.bearblog.dev/no-webweaving/</id>
    <title>I Don't Like Webweaving That Much TBH</title>
    <updated>2026-01-05T21:15:58.331893+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>haru-txt</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just spent the last hour trying to edit my current theme so that the navbar is on the side instead of the top, only to revert back to the old theme because I can't be bothered anymore to troubleshoot it. I wanted my blog list to have dates on the right so I copied &lt;a href="https://sylvia-dev.bearblog.dev/blog-list-with-dates-on-right-leading-dots/"&gt;Sylvia's&lt;/a&gt; code only for the blog list to have this unexplainable pure white background that I couldn't remove. At that point I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not the code's fault. I'm just a complete noob when it comes to HTML and CSS. But here's the thing: I don't really care to learn HTML/CSS. It seemed like a fun idea until I realise that trying to wrestle with the theming is getting in the way of what I &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; like: writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had 2 Neocities website. The first one, created in 2021 when I was active on Toyhouse, was supposed to be about my worldbuilding project. I never even add a CSS file to it. The second one was made in 2023 and was about pixel dollz. I actually tried to style the website a bit. But I quickly abandoned these two websites and completely forgot about them until today where I decided to write about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just... don't really care about webweaving as a hobby. I like the concept. I think we should have the freedom to write and style our own websites. I just don't find it particularly fun to sit and stare at hundreds lines of code that are somehow responsible for your website layout. I can if I must, but I really don't want to. What I want to do is post content: blogs, pictures, little pixel dollz that I drew with my own hands. To a lot of people on the indie web, the style &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the content. It's how they express their creativity and uniqueness. That's great! I love browsing other people's personal websites! But sadly it's just not for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future I might do something with my Neocities website. I deleted one and renamed the other to the same URL as this blog's. But at the end of the day I much prefer creating content over creating &lt;em&gt;websites&lt;/em&gt;, and maybe some of you reading this might be spending too much time trying to perfect your Bear Blog theme instead of actually writing too.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://haru-txt.bearblog.dev/no-webweaving/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-05T21:15:58.331893+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://pego.dev/overengineering-and-the-lost-art-of-common-sense/</id>
    <title>Overengineering and the Lost Art of Common Sense</title>
    <updated>2026-01-05T20:03:08.328438+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>pego</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There is a spectrum in software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one end you have Pieter Levels shipping real businesses with everything in a single index.php. On the other end you have teams building dozens of microservices, or worse, hundreds of “serverless” Lambdas, for a product that has maybe 100 concurrent users on a good day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And somewhere along the way, a lot of us forgot that the middle exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of my career I felt this, but I rarely said it out loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly because I always had this quiet insecurity in the background. I never went to university. I do not have a fancy computer science degree. So when the room got excited about “proper architecture”, I swallowed my thoughts. I assumed I must be missing something. Or that one day someone will expose me as the guy who does not really belong here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classic imposter syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I am getting close to 40 and I think I care less now. Not in a cynical way. More like, I finally trust my own experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here it is, on record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most startups do not need an overengineered system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not “some”. Not “many”. Almost all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I am not saying microservices are bad. Serverless is not bad either. These are tools. Powerful ones. If you need them, use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they should not be the default, especially early in a product’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that a lot of teams adopt “Netflix architecture” before they have Netflix problems. They pay the cost of complexity upfront, and they do it in exchange for benefits they might never receive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because architecture has a cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every extra service is another thing to deploy, monitor, secure, debug, version, document, test, and keep alive. Every boundary creates friction. Every abstraction adds distance between cause and effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At small scale, “distributed systems” often means “distributed confusion”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there is the biggest myth of them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that if you start super modular, everything will be easy later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That your microservices will behave like Lego blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That if the business pivots, you can just rearrange the blocks and keep building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In real life, this is often a lie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech debt accumulates in microservices too. Sometimes faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You still ship rushed decisions. You still cut corners. You still make assumptions under pressure. The only difference is that now those assumptions are spread across 20 repos, 40 deploy pipelines, and a web of contracts that you are scared to break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when the business changes direction, those “clean boundaries” are usually the first thing to fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because pivots do not respect your architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pivot changes data models. It changes workflows. It changes what “a user” even means. It changes the shape of the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the neat “lego blocks” you carefully built start fighting the new reality. Then you either glue them together with ugly hacks, or you rebuild them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the product is still trying to find basic fit. The users do not care about your event bus. They care about whether the thing works, whether it is fast, whether it is reliable, and whether they can trust it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a moment in a startup where you start believing you are building a spaceship, when you are still trying to get the wheels to stay on a bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get why it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microservices, serverless, Kubernetes, clean architecture diagrams. They signal seriousness. They look like competence. They make you feel like you are doing things the “right” way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And sometimes they also protect you socially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard to get criticized for following the current norm. If everyone is doing it, it must be correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But reality is more boring, and more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most products should start as a simple monolith. One deploy. One database. One place to look when things break. One codebase where you can refactor without negotiations between fifteen repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, when the pain becomes real, you earn complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not because it is fashionable, but because it is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always split later when you have proof. Proof of traffic, proof of team size, proof of scaling constraints, proof that a boundary is paying for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common sense approach is not “everything in one PHP file”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is not “a rabbit hole of AWS services”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is building the simplest thing that can grow, and only paying the price of complexity when you are forced to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds obvious, that is exactly the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is weird how often software culture drifts to extremes. Like we collectively forget that trade-offs exist, and that good engineering is usually boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, I am saying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;99% of startups will never need a microservice architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They would be better off somewhere in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it is not a revolutionary take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it is just what we used to call good judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://pego.dev/overengineering-and-the-lost-art-of-common-sense/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-05T20:03:08.328438+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://nobodysblog.bearblog.dev/i-am-not-an-artist/</id>
    <title>I am not an artist</title>
    <updated>2026-01-05T19:01:55.617181+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>nobodysblog</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am not an artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is that supposed to make my opinions on technology more valid? More respected?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an engineer. Will it change how you perceive my judgments?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am witnessing is the wide-scale deployment of technology so anti-consumer, so anti-human that it paints every day in a dark pall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say it is consumer preference. But those making the decisions own and operate all aspects of our lives. Total control of the fishbowl. There is no preference, just what they choose to push to market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely it is simply consumer preference to have our lives - our clothes, our food, our experiences, woven with synthetic plastics. To be lied to, to communicate with machines impersonating you, to interact with merely a compression of the sum of past works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not make this next statement lightly and understand the weight of it. The only English words I find to explain the rampant objectification of artists’ work, the violation of their intentions, and abuse of their rights, is the Rape of Art. Something that belongs to someone else has been ripped away from them and used in grotesque ways outside of the owner’s consent. A total violation, objectification of another human, for personal pleasure. It’s appalling. It’s abhorrent. It is a rot in our very lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tool that generates music, stolen from countless human-made songs? What do you think music is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tool that instantly modifies an artist’s work into what you want to see? Twists and distorts their work to be a reflection of your desires? What do you think art is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fake music, fake art, even fake correspondence! Nothing you will ever interact with will be intentional. Just a blurry sum of the past. Deceptions and the most statistically likely output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not an artist. But my disgust is born from being human, not from fear of losing my socioeconomic standing. How can you not feel it too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I think I am selfish. I selfishly want to live in a more beautiful and intentionally crafted world. I want the artists and tastemakers in the world to be rewarded. For any technology to be deployed, it must solve for creating a world worth participating in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want those who fill our communities and our world with color to be rewarded. I want to live in a world forged by the truly innovative - that means those who see this technology for what it is. The growing plasticization of our lives. Innovation only in the sense it is a new and creative way to milk the world’s population like the cattle they see us as.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to break out of the fishbowl created by the unimaginative, the spineless, and the cruel. They present this technology with smiles on their faces. That it’s for our benefit. It’s for progress. And that only increases my horror and disgust with their deranged villainry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think being human is?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual people are behind these features and tools being pushed. People who may even be your neighbor!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the spineless, the cruel, the unimaginative, who use and push this technology will continue to be rewarded. Those who wish to not degrade every aspect of our lives will have the fire lit and grow underneath them as they’re forced to compete economically against those profiting and setting new prices of everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will become a luxury to live in the world of the intentional. For you to be seen and treated as human in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people in charge of these technological “advancements” are not innovative. Their only true talent may be their ability to sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of this technology is not victimless. It is a grand violation of other human beings, their works, and the sanctity of their personhood. Some may laugh at this, insult me for using certain words, and dismiss it all as not that serious. It is serious. You should feel the weight of the crime being committed. But you first have to see that other people are living human beings in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consumer applications of this technology have been a criminal experiment using the lives of real people as test subjects. It must be terminated immediately through whatever pressures are possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This text that I have written with my hands, from my gut, are probably career suicide in an economy that rapidly seeks to demean consumers. And it is with that, I publish it with pride.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://nobodysblog.bearblog.dev/i-am-not-an-artist/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-05T19:01:55.617181+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.sherwoodcallaway.com/observability-s-past-present-and-future/</id>
    <title>Observability's Past, Present, and Future</title>
    <updated>2026-01-05T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>sherwood</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my last post, &lt;a href="https://blog.sherwoodcallaway.com/round-two/"&gt;Round Two&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote about my career, my passion for dev tools, and my decision to start a new company focused on observability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wrote about my frustration with observability as it exists today. Why are the tools and workflows so bad? Why does it feel like so much &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today's post, I want to unpack that frustration by looking at observability in historical context. I'll examine observability through a simple three-part lens: its past, present, and future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to understand and explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why observability emerged in the first place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How observability evolved into the mess it is today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why, despite all the progress we've made, maintaining reliable systems is still SO hard in 2026&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PART 1: OBSERVABILITY'S PAST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand observability, it helps to look at the environment that gave rise to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 2010s, software engineers faced a crisis: with the rise of cloud computing, containers, and microservices, apps were becoming increasingly complex - too complex for any individual to fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, CI/CD was becoming more common, which meant an increase in the rate at which changes were deployed to production. The result: more frequent bugs and outages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, our old reliability playbook stopped working. We couldn't predict all the edge-cases, let alone write tests for them. Failure modes increasingly emerged from the complex interaction between services. When it came to root-cause analysis, logs and basic metrics were no longer enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the industry found a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It came in two parts: a tool and a philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool was distributed tracing. After a quiet start in 2010, distributed tracing grew steadily over the ensuing decade until it was essentially ubiquitous:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010: Google publishes Dapper, the first major paper on distributed tracing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012: Twitter introduces Zipkin, inspired by Dapper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015: Honeycomb, one of the first managed tracing platforms, is founded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016: OpenTracing is adopted by CNCF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016: Uber introduces Jaeger, inspired by Zipkin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017: Datadog launches APM, their managed tracing solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2018: O'Reilly publishes &amp;quot;Distributed Systems Observability&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The philosophy was observability. Originally coined by a rocket scientist in the 1960s, the term &amp;quot;observability&amp;quot; was popularized in the software community by Twitter's engineering team during the early 2010s. It quickly grew into a full-fledged product category and engineering discipline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: Twitter publishes &amp;quot;Observability at Twitter&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2015: Charity Majors (Honeycomb founder) begins writing about observability, formalizing key concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2017: Peter Bourgon (Soundcloud engineer who worked on Prometheus) coins the &amp;quot;Three Pillars&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2022: O'Reilly publishes &amp;quot;Observability Engineering&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, distributed tracing gave engineers a way to debug modern apps, which were cloud-based and distributed by nature, while observability gave them the framework for how to think about reliability in this new operating environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point here is that observability wasn't born in a vacuum. It emerged as a response to real-world engineering challenges. And it persisted because, for the most part, it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then things took a turn for the worse. Encouraged by early results, engineering teams started to over-invest in observability tools and processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More instrumentation. More dashboards. More monitors. SLOs. Error budgets. Runbooks. Postmortems. By the early 2020s, observability was no longer a means to an end. It was an end unto itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PART 2: OBSERVABILITY'S PRESENT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, most engineers will agree: observability is table stakes. If you're running production systems at almost any scale, you need a way to detect, mitigate, and resolve issues when they occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the role of modern observability platforms like Datadog, Grafana, and Sentry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, when I think about the current state of observability, one question stands out: why, after 10+ years of investment in better tools and processes, does observability still suck?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm serious!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instrumentation takes forever. Dashboards are constantly out of date. Monitors misfire. Alerts lack context. On-call is a permanent tax on engineering productivity. Incident resolution can take hours, sometimes days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have more telemetry than ever, but getting an accurate mental model of your app in production is still a major challenge - not just for newgrads and vibe-coding Zoomers, but for experienced engineers too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not for lack of effort. At companies of all sizes, engineering teams take observability seriously, investing enormous amounts of time and energy into implementing and maintaining observability systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They shell out for Datadog. They instrument EVERYTHING. They adopt structured logging and enforced standardized naming/labeling conventions. They create &amp;quot;golden&amp;quot; dashboards. They painstakingly tune their monitors. By any reasonable definition, these teams are doing everything right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet there's a gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of effort we put into observability does NOT line up with the progress we've made towards its goals: better detection, faster root-cause analysis, and more reliable apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's because the real problem isn't about data, tooling, or process. It's about our ability - or inability - to understand and reason about the data we &lt;em&gt;already have&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observability made us very good at producing signals, but only slightly better at what comes after: interpreting them, generating insights, and translating those insights into reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PART 3: OBSERVABILITY'S FUTURE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's true that observability isn't living up to expectations. But that doesn't mean it's not useful or important. In fact, I believe observability is poised to become one of the most important technology categories of the coming decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason: software is changing again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2010s, observability emerged as an antidote to complexity. In 2026, software engineers face the largest complexity crisis we've ever come up against: AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is cutting the cost of writing code to zero. As a result, engineering teams are shipping vast amounts of features and at breakneck speeds. Codebases are getting bigger and bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, vibe-coding platforms have brought software development to the masses. More apps will be built and deployed this year than in all previous years combined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're on the verge of an &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/eIoohUmYpGI?si=o3CHH53RpkfJARLt"&gt;infinite software crisis&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises an uncomfortable question: how will we support, maintain, and operate this ever-growing mountain of software? I'm willing to bet the answer is observability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just not the version we have today...&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://blog.sherwoodcallaway.com/observability-s-past-present-and-future/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-05T16:00:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://bearblog.stevedylan.dev/sunsetting-my-bear-blog/</id>
    <title>Sunsetting my Bear Blog</title>
    <updated>2026-01-06T00:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>stevedylandev</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Those who have been following along may know that I started this blog as a way to escape social media and bring back an old form of online connections through blogs and RSS. In my opinion it has been super successful and I've thoroughly enjoyed meeting so many wonderful people. My list of feeds continue to grow as I follow more and more people, so never stop &lt;a href="mailto:contact@stevedylan.dev"&gt;reaching out&lt;/a&gt; if you want to say hi!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear Blog has been such a refreshing platform to post on as well; no qualms with it whatsoever. Herman is such a quality human being and I'll continue to push people towards this platform if they want to start blogging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only reason I'll probably stop posting here is my deep desire to return to building out my personal site. There's a lot of reasons as to why, and I think &lt;a href="https://henry.codes/writing/a-website-to-destroy-all-websites/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; says it better than I ever could. The practice of having a side blog in addition to my main blog has worked out well, but in the end I would rather put more work and effort into just one site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To that effect, I've actually built out something that lets me continue to push out updates that people can view or subscribe to through my &lt;a href="https://stevedylan.dev/now"&gt;now page&lt;/a&gt;, so if you want to keep seeing more content that you saw here, go &lt;a href="https://stevedylan.dev/now/rss.xml"&gt;subscribe&lt;/a&gt; and keep in touch! I made a little &lt;a href="https://stevedylan.dev/posts/using-atproto-for-posse"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; with the details. I'll leave all of my previous content here and running, just won't be posting new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Herman for Bear Blog &lt;br/&gt;
Thank you everyone who has followed this blog &lt;br/&gt;
Thank you to everyone who has sent an email &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever you do, keep writing blogs, keep using RSS, and keep the web open 🫡&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="reply-button-container"&gt;
  &lt;a class="reply-button" href="mailto:contact@stevedylan.dev?subject=Re: {{ post_title }}"&gt;reply via email&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://bearblog.stevedylan.dev/sunsetting-my-bear-blog/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-06T00:56:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://pego.dev/when-the-internet-felt-like-freedom/</id>
    <title>When the Internet Felt Like Freedom</title>
    <updated>2026-01-04T19:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>pego</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/pego/4837215146_qupy.webp" alt="il_794xN" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I went online, it felt like freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was no longer just a kid in a small Eastern European country. Suddenly I was part of the whole world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early internet was a blast. I feel very lucky to have lived in the 90s and to be there at the birth of the web. I could talk about dial-up modems and the strange beeping sounds when you tried to connect, but that was only the surface. The real change was deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was twelve when my dad showed me the internet. He did not fully understand it yet, but he felt that it was something big. He wanted his kids to see it early. I was very lucky to have access to a computer and the internet in his office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real turning point came one Christmas Eve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My sister and I got a small box. When I opened it, I started to cry. It is the first and last time I ever cried because of a present. Inside was a 56k modem and a card with a MATAV username and password for internet access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that day on I did not need to go to my dad’s office anymore. I could go online from my own bedroom on my 486 PC. Looking back, this was one of the biggest turning points in my life. Everything I have today comes from that moment. I still work on the web and build things online at 40.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that my days had a rhythm. Every afternoon at 16:00 a special tariff started. You could use the internet until the next morning for almost nothing. I remember sitting in my room, waiting for the clock to hit four, then listening to the modem sounds and feeling like the whole world just opened again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything changed again when I found IRC. For the first time I could talk to people from other countries in real time. It was magic. Today everyone carries the internet in their pocket, but back then this was unbelievable. A 13 year old kid from a small Hungarian city could talk to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went deep into a Hungarian hacker subculture around 1999. I still remember watching TV with my parents when the news reported that a hacker group had taken down the website of MATAV, the Hungarian telecom company. They replaced it with a punk style page that said Y2K in big Win95 Paint letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran to my computer to tell my IRC friends. The craziest part was that some people in my channel were part of that group. A few months later they told me parts of the story. It blew my mind. I was 13 and learning about the internet from the smartest kids in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am 40 now, but that kid is still inside me. Still curious. Still looking for people who think the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet has changed a lot. Big tech controls most of it now and the old feeling is hard to find. But sometimes I still discover small corners that feel like the early days. When that happens, it feels like a time machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I found Bearblog and it really clicked with me. I am not a great writer, but I want to share some thoughts and memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is my first post. Thank you Bearblog and the community. Even if nobody reads this, I will be reading you.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://pego.dev/when-the-internet-felt-like-freedom/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-04T19:37:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://jetgirl.art/why-does-modern-anime-look-so-washed-out/</id>
    <title>Why does modern anime look so washed out?</title>
    <updated>2026-01-07T05:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>jetgirl</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/jetgirl/v1.webp" alt="MV5BYWY4ZTEyOTUtNjhmMS00ZDMzLTk3MWItNmVjOTJiYTA3Zjg3XkEyXkFqcGc@" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day when I was watching Bugonia I noticed how intense the closeups were. Parts of their faces were in extreme focus, while everything else around them was blurry. This gave everything kind a dreamlike state flavor that worked for the show but I couldn't shake how awkward it was to watch the entire time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the director wants you to focus on or pay attention to is in crisp detailed focus, and everything else is mashed potatoes. I looked it up and apparently its due to the way films are made these days. Because typically the background is one solid color or one of those circular projection rooms they focus mainly on the character and what they are doing. Lighting is washed out so that everything can be glammed up in post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last bit got me thinking of how modern anime tends to look so washed out. I say modern anime but I noticed this shift in 2002. We were at an anime convention in Austin and one of the rooms was showing the debut of the &lt;em&gt;Azumanga Daioh&lt;/em&gt; anime. The first thing I noticed was this abrupt difference in the way the characters were painted. Colors were muted, outlines were no longer black and were very thin. The faces were wider, rounder, softer. I figured it was just the style of that one show and went on with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was used to anime drawn in the 80's and 90's. Bright colors with hard bold lines that mimicked the lines of the manga they were derived from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/jetgirl/oldanime.webp" alt="oldanime" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare this to modern anime where everything is muted and smooth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/jetgirl/modern.webp" alt="modern" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now not every anime is like this these days. Jojo and Demon Slayer are two that come to mind that still use bold linework and vibrant colors. Now, I am aware that older shows were manually painted and modern ones are digital. It does have a more natural look and feel to be washed out by light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also know that anime production is on a crazy schedule and they have to produce shows as fast as possible. I'm sure the color matching process on modern shows is down to a science. But so is modern film making. They can calibrate the world around two people in a green room. The computer will make it look as real as possible. But it still doesn't look &amp;quot;right&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old movies are shot and printed on film. Everything in a wide shot is in focus. You can pause the film and look at everything going on behind the characters. Close ups show dirt on the actors face instead of removing it in post. Colors are vibrant and reflect on natural and staged physical light. The contrast created is a matter of knowing how to use a camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like the old cell painted shows have that same feeling. Akira and Lawrence of Arabia both feel real, even though one is literally shot in the desert and another is painstakingly hand painted. Something about the grit of the linework mixed with the richness of photographed paint just gives it a warmth that make it so nice to look at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's that same bit of grit and intentional flourish you see when reading manga. You can see the brush strokes on the lines, the scratched down pen work. Looking at it feels the same as reading a hand written letter. It's far more personal.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://jetgirl.art/why-does-modern-anime-look-so-washed-out/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-07T05:51:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://pretendtypewriter.net/bring-back-emails-as-a-form-of-communication/</id>
    <title>BRING BACK EMAILS AS A FORM OF COMMUNICATION</title>
    <updated>2026-01-08T12:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>pretendtypewriter</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h4&gt;Let's take it back from marketers and spammers!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thought popped into my head last night. Ever since starting Bear Blog, I've been receiving emails from fellow bloggers, and it reminds me of my ==penpal== days, when we used to send snail mail to complete strangers—usually on the other side of the world—simply to connect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before starting this post, I did a quick search on Bear Blog's discovery to see if anyone else has written on the subject. Sure enough, &lt;a href="https://sebastianmalloy.bearblog.dev/"&gt;Sebastian&lt;/a&gt; wrote a post titled, &amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://sebastianmalloy.bearblog.dev/emails-are-making-me-happy-again/"&gt;Emails Are Making Me Happy Again&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;quot; which perfectly summarizes all of my thoughts. So rather than just repeat what he wrote, I'll add on another take:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Texting isn't the best way to communicate detailed information.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have many forms of communication at our disposal today, and I believe each has its purpose. Texting is great for casual chatting or even long-winded conversations. ==But texting really fails at sending useful chunks of information.== In fact, if I received a bunch of links and info via text, I might find it overwhelming, but I'd mostly just FORGET about it. I mainly use Whatsapp, and while you can star specific messages, it's not the best at saving information, and most of the time, I simply just don't remember that it's there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;But emails!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could send all that info in one go. It could be a list of links, an essay, or even span multiple threads. But it's all there, bundled together by an appropriately titled subject line. Emails are there forever, and even for an unorganized inbox, one can simply search via keywords, which isn't as easy to do on Whatsapp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm one of those people with only one email for everything. I mostly shop online, so I appreciate emails when my order has shipped. I worry that if I had multiple accounts, I'd forget to to check them. And if I forwarded all of those emails to my main... Well, what's the point of having multiple accounts in the first place?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the topic of emails, I am also keen on de-Googling my life. However, it's difficult and will take some time. I would also need to do some research, and right now, looking into email clients is not on my priority list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;(Perhaps I will make a list of the tech and apps I use. I love seeing what other people I using, and I get a little bit more techy each day.)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, echoing the words of my fellow Bear Bloggers who love receiving emails, I love them too! I used to spend time organizing my inbox, but ever since it fell by way of marketers, I stopped caring. Now, I feel motivated to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, remember when we used to send email chains? I don't miss that format, but that's when I first started seeing content like, &amp;quot;25 facts about me,&amp;quot; etc. etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only are more and more people yearning for the analog life, we're also collectively yearning for the early days of the internet, back when it was messy, imperfect, and clearly made by humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/2025-food-highlights/"&gt;Previous&lt;/a&gt; |&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://pretendtypewriter.net/bring-back-emails-as-a-form-of-communication/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-08T12:33:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://taylorstimes.bearblog.dev/self-hosting/</id>
    <title>self hosting</title>
    <updated>2026-01-08T00:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>taylorstimes</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just read &lt;a href="tab:https://blog.salcyeka.com/the-abrupt-interruption"&gt;Eka's post&lt;/a&gt; about growing weary of self hosting. It's funny because I just reached out to fellow blogger &lt;a href="tab:https://www.neuronetch.com/"&gt;Khem&lt;/a&gt; because in one of his posts he spoke about self hosting music. I love the parity that you find here on Bear Blog. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m tired of paying these companies—companies that keep raising their prices—when it’s within my capacity to host my own services, ie. photo storage via &lt;a href="tab:https://immich.app/"&gt;Immich&lt;/a&gt;, or music via &lt;a href="tab:https://www.navidrome.org/"&gt;Navidrome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own tolerance for friction, and that friction comes in different forms; whether that be monetarily, time commitment, or frustration. For me, I find the friction of self-hosting to be fun, and something that is worth my downtime over things like scrolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, I enjoy reading everyone's posts on here and getting to know differing ways people go about living life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:me@taylorjgibson.com?subject=Re:%20{{ post_title }}"&gt;Reply via email&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

</content>
    <link href="https://taylorstimes.bearblog.dev/self-hosting/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-08T00:26:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://vespertine.bearblog.dev/retired-from-sad/</id>
    <title>retired from sad, new career in law</title>
    <updated>2026-01-04T22:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>vespertine</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;my first semester of law school didn't pan out the way i'd hoped. the time for introspection was probably three weeks ago, so now i'm just rocking myself through the aftershocks of failure and attempting to formulate some semblance of a gameplan for salvaging my average over the next few years. it feels bad, not just because jobhunting will be so much harder, but also because this past semester felt like my last chance to prove something to myself—that i can meet my own expectations, live diligently, and achieve the conventional kind of success my mother yearns to flaunt amongst the other aunties after sunday service. grad school doesn't come free, and with academic vindication so far off, i feel like i'm not making the best use of my accumulating debt (or dwindling &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;good&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot; years). the opportunity cost is too high for me to be fumbling this spectacularly, and it's been disappointing to confront the reality that i'm no longer as high-functioning in high-pressure situations as i used to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yesterday, i went on a 2-hour walk with my mother and she told me that, quite frankly, she doesn't know what do with me. aren't i devastated by the long-term downward trajectory of my life? don't i want better for myself? for her? she's humored me with the liberal arts/neurodivergence/biting-her-tongue bullshit for long enough (give or take 3 years), so where are the results? one of my younger cousins scored top 10 in her high school class of hundreds for physics and math, you know, and she's been wechatting my mother to ask for advice about pursuing a career in medicine. imagine where i'd be now if i had just taken that advice to heart and actually applied myself! she's certain that the untapped potential for neurosurgery is still hidden within me somewhere, lying dormant, waiting to be activated by the right canon event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to be honest, i don't think my mother will ever emotionally recover from my decision to eschew medicine in favor of finance, and then finance in favor of law. i probably could've softened the blow by going to a better law school or performing marginally better on my final exams, but nothing will change the fact that i'll never have comma-space-M-D written after my name. it's no secret that i'm frustrated by how poorly i performed this semester, so no matter how immeasurable my mother's disappointment might seem, my own disappointment dwarfs hers by magnitudes. logically, i know that i will likely undergo several more career pivots prior to retirement, but right now, law school feels like my last chance to carve out a meaningful inflection point and reverse the lemony snicket circus direction my life has been heading in. it's been a long time since i was last a full-time student, and i want to do well for my own sake—by graduating after 3 years of sincere effort that i can be genuinely proud of. pride isn't something i've been positively moved by in over a decade, but it'd be nice to know that i'm still capable of meeting my own expectations (and further, necessary to build up trust in my own self-control). very few aspects of my life are within my control, so i need to do what i can to turn the tide in my favor (': i can't be fighting myself and the world at the same time...if nobody got me, at least i know that i've got me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i don't usually do new year's resolutions, but i have tried to gradually implement some positive changes to my lifestyle over the past 2 months that i hope to sustain in 2026:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;going to sleep before midnight and waking up before 7 am. whatever i want/need to do during witching hour can get done in the morning, even if it's just reading for fun. i find that i'm less likely to doomscroll for hours on end when i'm online at the crack of dawn, as opposed to tw*tter rabbithole mining in the dead of night, and even if i'm awake for the same total number of hours during the day, at least i'm getting more sunlight than before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;checking the weather and selecting my outfit the night before. i cannot trust myself to make slayful, professional wardrobe choices while groggily stumbling through my closet in the morning, because i usually end up defaulting to the same oversized cardigans, neutral tees, and wide-legged pants with elasticized waistbands. there are neatly folded stacks of cute, comfy clothes in my closet that have never seen the light of day due to my stubborn refusal to use any critical thinking skills before noon, and this has been helping me cycle through more of them with each passing week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;standing/walking while passively watching/reading things. i have two standing desks in my apartment, neither of which had been used in standing mode prior to october of last year. my class schedule requires me to sit in a lecture hall from 9-5 and read hundreds of pages per week, and most of the other hobbies i usually do while sitting could be enjoyed equally while standing. in the interest of preventing an early death due to my excessively sedentary lifestyle (amongst other unhealthy habits), i've started standing more indoors and using my walking pad while watching TV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spending less time reading textbooks and more time writing practice exams. if the past semester has taught me anything, it's that i'm only graded on what i manage to type out during my final exam, not the hundreds of pages of notes i painstakingly took before/during/after class. i need to work smarter, not harder, and get a better feel for my professors' grading preferences before i actually sit for their exams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and a speed-run through some other goals for this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read at least 24 books. i set my goodreads goal at 12 because i only managed to get through 15 in 2025, but i've already read another in the past two days and i'm optimistic about my tbr lineup for this year. getting back into physical copies has helped, somewhat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;visit my maternal grandparents. i'm hoping to squeeze in a 2-week trip between the end of spring semester finals and the beginning of my summer internship (crossing my fingers that i'll even have one...), but if it doesn't work out, i'll probably fly out in december. maybe i'll even drop by taiwan on the way!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get involved with volunteering in my local community. it's been a few months since i moved here for school, and now that i've familiarized myself with the area, i'd really like to serve the folks around me through an immigration or social work-adjacent nonprofit program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stop being such an antisocial cave hermit! i need to start saying yes when people invite me to things and proactively check in on people more often. making friends certainly does not get easier as an adult, and i'm not doing myself any favors by holing myself up in my apartment 24/7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the world is going up in flames, but that doesn't mean we should all lay down and await the sweet embrace of apocalypse. even though it may feel futile at times, trying will always be worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;assuredly,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;t&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://vespertine.bearblog.dev/retired-from-sad/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-04T22:12:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.lauramichet.com/im-very-angry-today/</id>
    <title>I'm very angry today!</title>
    <updated>2026-01-04T02:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>lauram</name>
      <email>hidden</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, Trump's government executed an &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/q-and-a/the-brazen-illegality-of-trumps-venezuela-operation"&gt;extraordinarily illegal&lt;/a&gt; kidnapping of a foreign head of state. Any US government official that is not calling for his impeachment is an embarrassment and should be primaried. This includes anyone who bothers to acknowledge the illegal operation's PR framing by discussing whether they dislike Maduro or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll feel safe in this country again when the people involved in planning and carrying out this event have been tried and jailed and, where appropriate, executed by the state. I don't believe that the state should be able to execute civilians for any reason at all - name any crime, and I'm against killing civilians for it - but I do genuinely believe that government officials should be executed for committing war crimes specifically. It's a form of anti-death-penalty politics that we can maybe call &amp;quot;The Guys In Power Should Be Scared.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes an extraordinary lack of fear to do something like this. You should be thinking about what they're not scared enough to not do next - these guys themselves have been mentioning countries like Mexico and Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should also be thinking a lot, all the time, about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_trials"&gt;what it would take&lt;/a&gt; to make guys like Hegseth too scared to terrorize you and your siblings overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because he's not scared of Congress, and he's not scared of the UN. Guys with raw power who aren't scared are your enemies. They want you poor and sick and angry, and they want your kids to die overseas, and they don't think of brown people born south of Texas as &lt;em&gt;human.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <link href="https://blog.lauramichet.com/im-very-angry-today/" rel="alternate"/>
    <published>2026-01-04T02:57:00+00:00</published>
  </entry>
</feed>